"How Much Cancer Does Processed Meat Cause?"
In 2018, arguably the most
prestigious cancer research institution
in the world, the International Agency
for Research on Cancer (IARC),
within the World Health Organization,
published their report
on processed meat, concluding
that foods like bacon, ham,
hot dogs, lunch meat, and
sausages are cancer causing,
classifying processed meat
as a Group 1 carcinogen.
“These findings,” concluded
the director of the agency,
“further support current
public health recommendations
to limit the intake of meat.”
Critics questioned putting
processed meat in the same
carcinogenic classification
as asbestos or tobacco.
Or as a pesticide company
roughly put it, how can eating
processed meat fall into the
same category as mustard gas.
The classifications only relate
to the strength of evidence
that the agent causes cancer
or not, not how much cancer.
This does not mean that
they are all equally dangerous.
It’s safer to eat a sandwich
filled with pastrami than plutonium,
even though they are both
Group 1 carcinogens;
both substances known to
cause cancer in people.
Okay, so just how
dangerous is meat?
The relative risk of colorectal
cancer was 18 percent
for every 50 grams a day. Okay,
so what exactly does that mean?
Well, 50 grams is about one hot
dog, or two breakfast links,
or two slices of
Canadian bacon or ham.
So, a daily sandwich with one
or two slices of baloney
would increase your colorectal
cancer risk by 18 percent.
But a half-pound
pastrami on rye would
bump it up more like 80 percent.
Okay, but what does the 18 percent
increased risk really mean?
One way to look at it is
absolute risk versus relative risk.
Assuming that the lifetime
risk of colorectal cancer is
about 5 percent (1 in 20),
increasing your risk about
20 percent would only
bump up your absolute risk
of getting colorectal cancer
from 5 percent to 6 percent.
Now, on a population scale,
an 18 percent drop in risk
could mean about 20,000 fewer
cases of colorectal cancer
every year in the United States,
20,000 fewer families a year
dealing with that diagnosis,
if we swapped out the daily
bologna sandwich for hummus or
chose veggie dogs instead.
So, it all depends on
how you look at it.
Colorectal cancer is our second
leading cause of cancer death
for men and women combined,
after lung cancer.
So, if you don’t smoke,
colon and rectal cancer
may be your greatest cancer nemesis.
But we can drop the risk
of getting it by about a fifth
with a single dietary tweak:
cutting a serving of
processed meat out of our daily diet.
How does 18 percent
increased cancer risk
compare to other risky behavior?
In my testimony before the Dietary
Guidelines Scientific Committee,
I made what may sound
like a hyperbolic metaphor.
I asked, “We try not to
smoke around our kids,
why would we send them to
school with a baloney sandwich?”
That is not hyperbole.
According to the Surgeon
General, living with a smoker
increases your risk of
lung cancer by 15 percent.
So, breathing second-hand
smoke day in and day out
increases your risk of lung
cancer almost as much as
eating a serving of processed
meat day in and day out
increases your risk
of colorectal cancer.
The meat industry responded
by saying that the risks
and benefits must be
considered together before
telling people what to eat or breathe.
Think about all the baloney benefits.
Lunch meat isn’t just about
cancer but convenience.
Indeed, processed meat
isn’t just about cancer.
An article railing against
the World Health Organization’s
“meat terrorism” cited the
Global Burden of Disease studies
comparing how many cancer deaths
are caused by processed meat
consumption compared to
tobacco or alcohol use.
But if you look at the
study they’re referencing,
the 30-something thousand
deaths attributable to higher
processed meat intake are
just the colorectal cancer deaths,
and don’t also include the
100,000 deaths from diabetes
or the 400,000 deaths from heart disease.
So, in actuality, we may be
talking a half million deaths
attributable to processed meat.
And it’s not just
colon and rectal cancer.
If you look at the science since
the IARC decision was published,
processed meat may also
increase the risk of
prostate cancer, breast cancer,
and pancreatic cancer.
Unfortunately, despite growing
public health concerns
about processed meat consumption,
there have been no changes
in the amount of processed
meat consumed by U.S. adults
over the last 18 years.
Of course, it would
have helped if the last
Dietary Guidelines for Americans
had happened to mention
that processed meat was a carcinogen.
An explicit and science-based
statement on processed meat
in the next Dietary Guidelines
would certainly help.
But the scientific committee
made no such recommendation.
Sadly, even those diagnosed with
colorectal cancer hardly improve
their overall lifestyle after
diagnosis, though that may be
because “70 percent of cancer
patients had never received
nutrition advice from
their [medical] providers
during or after treatment.”
That just blows me away.
“Despite the continued
obfuscation of the issue
by the meat industry—they learned
well from the tobacco merchants—
meat should continue to be
a focus of public health action.”
New York City is leading
the way, passing legislation
to ban processed meats
from school meals.
What a concept, not giving
our kids carcinogens.
Meanwhile, the processed
meat industry
is trying to reformulate its products.
It’s kind of like in
the pharmaceutical area,
where you try to mitigate
the potential adverse effects
of one drug by prescribing
an additional drug.
Like you could add fiber to
hot dogs or something to try
to counterbalance the risk,
potentially reducing the cancer load
by changing how it’s
processed rather than by
banning processed meat altogether.